<appendix>
	<title>Output Specification Appendix</title>

    <para>
      This section specifies and documents the output of EPL continuous queries for two purposes: First, to standarize EPL output for EPL queries in a testable and trackable fashion, since no such standard exists today. Second, to help application developers understand streaming engine output in response to incoming events and in response to time passing.
    </para>

    <para>
      The section focuses on a subset of features, namely the time window, aggregation, grouping, having-clause and output rate limiting. The section does not currently provide examples for many of the other language features, thus there is no example for other data windows, joins, subselects or named windows, to name a few.
    </para>

    <para>
      Rather then just describe output, this section provides detailed examples for each of the cases presented. The input for each case is always the same set of events, and the same timing between events. Each event has three properties: symbol, volume and price. The property types are string, long and double, respectively.
    </para>

    <para>
      The input events and their timing are below. The table should be read, starting from top, as "The time starts at 0.2 seconds. Event E1 arrives at 0.2 seconds with properties {S1, 100, 25). At 0.8 second event E2 arrives with properties {S2, 5000, 9.0}." and so on. 
    </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
Statement:
  select symbol, volume, price from MarketData.win:time(5.5 sec)

                       Input                                  
-----------------------------------------------  
 Time Symbol  Volume   Price
  0.2                          
          S1     100    25.0   Event E1 arrives
  0.8                          
          S2    5000     9.0   Event E2 arrives
  1.0                          
  1.2                          
  1.5                          
          S1     150    24.0   Event E3 arrives
          S3   10000     1.0   Event E4 arrives
  2.0                          
  2.1                          
          S1     155    26.0   Event E5 arrives
  2.2                          
  2.5                          
  3.0                          
  3.2                          
  3.5                          
          S3   11000     2.0   Event E6 arrives
  4.0                          
  4.2                          
  4.3                          
          S1     150    22.0   Event E7 arrives
  4.9                          
          S3   11500     3.0   Event E8 arrives
  5.0                          
  5.2                          
  5.7                          Event E1 leaves the time window
  5.9                          
          S3   10500     1.0   Event E9 arrives
  6.0                          
  6.2                          
  6.3                          Event E2 leaves the time window
  7.0                          Event E3 and E4 leave the time window
  7.2                          
]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      The event data set assumes a time window of 5.5 seconds. At time 5.7 seconds the first arriving event (E1) leaves the time window.
    </para>

    <sect1 id="app_spec_exampledata" revision="1">
        <title>Output</title>

		<para>
		  The section first introduces the  
		  is based on an example out of the trading domain. 
		  predefined event data set consisting of market data events. Each 
		  and timing between events constants. 
		</para>
    </sect1>

</appendix>
