<chapter id="architecture">

    <title>Architecture</title>

    <sect1 id="architecture-overview" revision="1">
        <title>Overview</title>
        
        <para>
            A (very) high-level view of the architecture: TODO
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="building_testing" revision="1">
        <title>Building and Testing</title>
        
        <para>
            The Esper code base consists of about 300 source code and 270 unit test (as of release 0.7.0) or test support classes, excluding examples. After build there are over 500 unit test methods that are automatically run to verify the build. Some of the unit tests assert against performance data taken during the test. These tests are designed to run on a single 2.8 GHz Pentium 4 processor with 512MB memory.
        </para>

        <para>
            Esper requires the following 3rd-party libraries:
        </para>
        
		<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					ANTLR is the parser generator used for parsing and parse tree walking of the pattern and EQL syntax. Credit goes to Terence Parr at http://www.antlr.org. The ANTLR license is in the lib directory. The library is required for compile-time only.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					CGLIB is the code generation library for fast method calls. This open source software is under the Apache license. The Apache 2.0 license is in the lib directory.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					LOG4J and Apache commons logging are logging components. This open source software is under the Apache license. The Apache 2.0 license is in the lib directory.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					BeanUtils is a JavaBean manipulation library. This open source software is under the Apache license. The Apache 2.0 license is in the lib directory.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					JUnit is a great unit testing framework. Its license has also been placed in the lib directory. The library is required for build-time only.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

    </sect1>

</chapter>

